Finding aid for Association for Asian Studies records, 1947-1988
Bentley Historical Library
Association for Asian Studies records
1947-1988
Bentley Historical Library
Association for Asian Studies.
8541 Bp 2
48.5 linear feet
Minutes, correspondence files, memoranda, financial material, and other miscellanea relating to the work of the organization.
The records were received from the Association (donor no. 5965 ) in multiple accession beginning in 1976.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The origins of the Association for Asian Studies began with the publication of the Bulletin of Far Eastern Bibliography in 1936. The Bulletin was expanded in a more comprehensive journal in 1941 and renamed The Far Eastern Quarterly. This publication was supported by a small committee of scholars who had organized themselves as the Far Eastern Association.
Because of continued financial difficulties, a special meeting was held in 1948 and the committee, along with some invited guests, discussed the possibility of reorganizing the Association as an active membership organization. The first meeting of the reorganized Association was held in New York City on April 2, 1948. Arthur W. Hummell of the Library of Congress was elected the Association's first president.
The objectives of the Association were:
To form a scholarly, nonpolitical, and nonprofit professional association of all persons interested in the study of the Far East.
To promote interest in and scholarly study of the Far East.
To provide means for the publication of scholarly research and other materials designed to promote Far Eastern studies.
To promote cooperative activities and exchange of information within the filed of Far Eastern studies in the United States and Canada.
To facilitate contact and exchange of information between scholars and scholarly organizations interested in Far Eastern Studies in North America and in other countries.
In December 1949 the board of directors decided to seek new sources of revenue to expand the organization's scope. The board prioritized the purposes of these funds as:
The publication of research.
The maintenance of a permanent secretariat.
The support of scholarships and fellowships.
The support of summer institutes on Far Eastern studies for non-specialist teachers.
Initial funding was achieved by raising membership dues, however the Research Committee on Development of Far Eastern Studies was created for the purpose of exploring foundation support for these activities. By the end of 1955 the Committee's work led to substantial funding for the Association through the Ford Foundation. Ford Foundation's support was generous; subsidizing the expansion of the society's journal, the establishment of a monograph series, the publication of a newsletter, the maintenance of a secretariat, and the work of various Association committees. By 1960 outside funding had made possible an increased level of activity and stability within the Association.
In 1956 the Far Eastern Association was renamed the Association for Asian Studies (AAS), the Far Eastern Quarterly was re-titled the Journal of Asian Studies, and the constitution and bylaws were amended to incorporate south Asia into the sphere of the Association's interest and activity. To reflect this latter change the Association's board of directors was expanded from nine to twelve members, with three seats on the board reserved for south Asian specialists.
Membership growth and the expanded geographic interest of the Association led to the formation of areas study committees in the mid-1950's. The first to be well established was the Committee on South Asia, which in 1956 received a large grant from the Rockefeller Foundation, enabling it to sponsor a number of organizational meetings of South Asian specialists. Broad umbrella committees such as the Committee on South Asia were further subdivided by the development of even more specialized committees, such as the Ceylon Studies Committee, the Bengal Studies Committee, the Gandhi Centennial Committee, and the Ghalib Centenary Committee, all of which sponsored their own conferences, lectures and publications. The pattern established by the South Asian Committee was replicated in other parts of the Association. In 1962, for example, the Committee on Southeast Asia was established. It quickly developed subcommittees such as the Burma Study Group, the Language Resources Committee, and the Indonesia Studies Committee. By 1969-1970 two other broad groups, representing scholarly interest in Northeast Asia and China and Inner Asia had been formed. They, and their predecessors in the fields of Southeast Asia and South Asia, were formally recognized in 1969/70 by the designation "Regional Councils".
The link between the AAS and the University of Michigan is rooted in the strong bonds of service that grew between UM faculty members interested in Asian Studies and the Association. Beginning in 1952 a succession of UM faculty served in the AAS secretariat. In 1955 the Association's board of director's voted to establish a permanent Secretariat and locate it in Ann Arbor.
Summary Contents List
Foundational documents
Founding Papers and History, 1947-1948 (box 1)
Secretariat and other administrative offices
1948-1970
Board of Directors, 1948-1970 (boxes 1-3)
Executive Committee, 1949-1970 (box 3)
President, 1948-1971 (box 3)
Secretary, 1948-1966 (box 3-4)
Secretary-Treasurer, 1968-1971 (box 4)
Administrative Secretary, 1968-1970 (box 4)
Treasurer, 1948-1970 (box 4)
Editors, 1950-1971 (boxes 4-5)
Committees (boxes 5-11)
Grants (box 11)
Miscellaneous (boxes 11-13)
Language and Area Studies Review (boxes 13-14)
Far East Association Meetings, 1949-1968 (boxes 14-15)
Regional Meetings and Conferences (box 15)
International Congress of Orientalists (box 16)
Lectures (box 17)
1949-1985 (primarily 1970-1979; not all headings listed)
Administrative Officer Correspondence, 1971-1980 (boxes 18-19)
Annual Meetings, 1949-1974 (boxes 20-22)
Board of Directors, 1961-1979 (boxes 22-23)
Presidents (box 22)
Secretary-Treasurer (boxes 22-23)
Board Minutes (box 23)
Committees, 1960-1981 (boxes 24-28)
ABC East, 1967-1974 (box 24)
Executive, 1960-1978 (boxes 24-25)
Information Control, 1969-1971 (box 25)
Publications, 1961-1983 (boxes 25-28)
Bibliography of Asian Studies, 1969-1983 (boxes 25-26)
Journal of Asian Studies, 1970-1980 (boxes 26-27)
Monographs, 1971-1978 (boxes 27-28)
International Congress of Orientalists, 1967 (box 29)
Newsletters, primarily 1971-1985, (box 29-30)
1951-1983: General Subjects and Grants
General Subjects (box 42)
Grants (boxes 43-45)
1952-1989: General Subjects and Grants
General Subjects (boxes 47-48)
Grants (boxes 48-49)
Regional Councils
China and Inner Asia Regional Council
Topical Files
1961-1980 (box 31)
1971-1980 (box 45-47)
Northeast Asia Regional Council, 1970-1980 (box 32)
Topical Files, 1970-1980 (box 32)
Studies Groups and Area Committees, 1970-1975 (box 32)
Grants Received (box 49)
South Asia Regional Council, 1955-1978 (boxes 32-36)
Topical Files, 1968-1979 (boxes 32-35)
Studies Groups and Committees, 1969-1977 (boxes 35-36)
Afghanistan Committee, 1973-1976 (box 35)
Bangladesh Committee, 1972-1976 (box 35)
Institutional Liaison Committee, 1969-1977 (box 35)
Language and Literature Development Committee, 1969-1977 (box 35)
Nepal Committee, 1972-1978 (box 35)
Pakistan Committee, 1970-1976 (boxes 35-36)
Sri Lanka Committee, 1972-1976 (box 36)
Regional Council Affiliates, 1968-1980 (box 36)
Miscellaneous (box 47)
Southeast Asia Regional Council, 1968-1982 (boxes 36-41)
Topical Files, 1968-1981 (boxes 36-39)
Studies Groups and Committees, 1969-1982 (boxes 39-41)
The records of the Association for Asian Studies have been arranged into three series: Foundational documents; Secretariat and other administrative offices; and Regional Councils. Although the records have been received over a period of years, this finding aid attempts to bring together like materials. Even so, the researcher is encouraged to examine the container listing thoroughly for similar materials received at different times.
Asia.; Photographs.; Association for Asian Studies.; Association for Asian Studies.
- Foundational documents
  The Foundational documents include the constitution and materials relating to the founding of the Far East Association.
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Founding of the Far East Association, 1947-1948; 2 folders (Box 1)
- Secretariat and other administrative offices
  Governance files have been drawn together into the Secretariat and other administrative offices series. This series is further divided into chronological subseries. Unfortunately, there is much overlapping of dates and topics. In this series, the researcher will find board of directors and executive committee meeting files, correspondence and memoranda of the Association's presidents, secretaries, and other officers. Also included are committee files, grants, and miscellaneous office material. The language and area studies review files concerns professional organizations and projects. There are also meeting files of the Far Eastern Association and documentation of regional meetings and conferences.
  - 1948-1970
    - Board of Directors' Files
      (include memos, minutes, annual reports, and annual meeting materials)
      - Miscellaneous Papers, 1948-1951; 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Board meeting, 1948-1959; 17 folders (Box 1)
      - 1960-1969, 28 folders (Box 2)
      - 1970 (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee Files
      (includes memos, minutes and correspondence)
      - 1949-1950 (Box 3)
      - 1952 (Box 3)
      - 1957 (Box 3)
      - 1958, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - 1962 (Box 3)
      - 1966 (Box 3)
      - 1970 (Box 3)
    - President files
      (includes correspondence and memos)
      - Hummel, Arthur W., 1948-1949 (Box 3)
      - Gardner, Charles S., 1949-1950 (Box 3)
      - Quigley, Harold S., 1950-1951 (Box 3)
      - Hall, Robert B., 1951-1952 (Box 3)
      - Emerson, Rupert, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
      - Goodrich, Carrington, 1956-1957; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Borton, Hugh, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
      - Fairbank, John K., 1958-1959 (Box 3)
      - Cressey, George B., 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Brown, Norman W., 1960-1961; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Pritchard, Earl H., 1962-1963 (Box 3)
      - Lockwood, William W., 1963-1964 (Box 3)
      - Wright, Arthur F., 1964-1965 (Box 3)
      - Pelzer, Karl J., 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Furber, Holden, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
      - deBary, William Theodore, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
      - DeBois, Cora, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    - Secretary files
      - Fairbank,Wilma, 1948-1949; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Yamagiwa, Joseph, 1949-1950; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Biggerstaff, Knight, 1950-1952 (Box 4)
      - Ward, Robert E., 1952-1953; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Anderson, Ronald, 1953-1959 (Box 4)
      - Crane, Robert I., 1959-1961 (Box 4)
      - Fifield, Russell, 1961-1963 (Box 4)
      - Gosling, L.A., 1963-1966 (Box 4)
    - Secretary-Treasurer files
      - Steinberg, David J., 1968-1970 (Box 4)
      - Park, Richard, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Annual reports of the secretary (Box 4)
      - Membership statistics (Box 4)
      - Library construction plans (Box 4)
    - Administrative Secretary files (correspondence)
      - Steinberg, David, 1968 (Box 4)
      - Richmond, Henry, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Treasurer files
      (includes memos and correspondence)
      - Borton, Hugh, 1948-1951 (Box 4)
      - Wilbur, C. Martin, 1951-1954 (Box 4)
      - Kublin, Hyman, 1954-1961; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Patrick, Hugh, 1964-1970; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Annual reports, 1949-1970 (Box 4)
      - Certified Public Accountants Audits, 1957-1969 (Box 4)
    - Editor's files: Journal of Asian Studies
      - Pritchard, Earl, 1948-1951; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Crane, Robert, 1965 (Box 4)
      - Harrison, John, 1969-1970; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Selection of editor, 1950-1952 (Box 5)
      - Far Eastern Quarterly, 1953 (Box 5)
      - Reports of Journal Editors, 1954-1968 (Box 5)
    - Editor's Files: Bibliography of Asian Studies
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Howard, Richard (Box 5)
      - Annual reports, 1963-1968 (Box 5)
      - Thein Swe, associate editor, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Editor's files: AAS Newsletter
      - Gordon, L.D., editor, 1970-1971; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Annual reports, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Editor's files: Monograph Series
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Monograph Board (FEA) (Box 5)
      - Kracke, E.A., editor, 1954-1957 (Box 5)
      - Brown, Delmer, editor, 1960-1965 (Box 5)
      - Wheatley, Paul, editor, 1965; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Annual reports (Box 5)
    - Committee Files
      - Advisory Committee on Research and Development, 10 folders (Box 5)
      - Nominating Committee, 18 folders (Box 6)
      - Program Committee, 15 folders (Box 6)
      - Association Committee Files: (Box 7)
      - American Council of Learned Societies, 13 folders (Box 7)
      - Automated Bibliographical Control Project, 6 folders (Box 7)
      - Bengal Studies Committee (Box 7)
      - Bibliographical Committee (Box 7)
      - Buddhist Studies Committee (Box 7)
      - Committee Lists (Box 7)
      - Committee of Chinese Language Teachers Association (Box 7)
      - Committee of Concerned Asian Scholars (Box 7)
      - Committees of the Association (Box 7)
      - Committee on American Library Resources on South and Southeast Asia (Box 7)
      - Committee on American Library Resources on Southern Asia (Box 7)
      - Committee on American Library Resources on Southeast Asia (Box 8)
      - Committee on American Library Resources on the Far East
        - General, 5 folders (Box 8)
        - National Science Foundation Grant, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Social Science Research Council Grant (Box 8)
      - Committee on Asian Law (Box 8)
      - Committee on Asian Prehistory (Box 8)
      - Committee on Chinese Thought (Box 8)
      - Committee on East Asian Libraries, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Committee on Information Control (Box 8)
      - Committee on Japanese Language Teaching (Box 8)
      - Committee on Reorganization (Box 8)
      - Committee on Research Materials on Southeast Asia, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Committee on the Relations of Learned Societies to American Education, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Committee on Summer Programs (Box 9)
      - Committee on Transition (Box 9)
      - Committee Personnel, 1968 (Box 9)
      - Committee reports (Box 9)
      - Disciplinary Associations (Box 9)
      - East Asian Comparative Literature Committee (Box 9)
      - Ethics Committee (Box 9)
      - Finance Committee, 4 folders (Box 9)
      - Funding Committee (Box 9)
      - Gandhi Centennial Committee (Box 9)
      - Honorary Committee (Box 9)
      - International Liaison Committee, 4 folders (Box 9)
      - Interuniversity Committee on Southeast Asia, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Japanese War Documents Report (Box 10)
      - Joint Committee on Far Eastern Collections (Box 10)
      - Joint Committee on Japanese Studies (Box 10)
      - Joint Far East Association and American Library Association Committee (Box 10)
      - Korean Studies Committee, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Membership Committee, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - Ming Project Committee, 4 folders (Box 10)
      - Reorganization Committee (Box 10)
      - Romanization Committee (Box 10)
      - Secondary Education Committee, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - South Asia Language Committee, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - South Asia Committee, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - Southeast Asia Committee, 4 folders (Box 11)
      - Undergraduate Education Committee (Box 11)
    - Grant files
      - American Council of Learned Societies Travel Grants (Box 11)
      - Association of Asian Studies Grants (Box 11)
      - Ford Foundation Grants, 5 folders (Box 11)
      - National Endowment for the Humanities (Box 11)
      - National Science Foundation (Box 11)
      - Project Committees-Basic Documents, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Rockefeller Foundation Book Grant, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - U Nu Grant (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous Files
      (includes conference and project files)
      - International Congress (Box 11)
      - Cooperation with Other Organizations (Box 11)
      - Japanese War Documents (Box 11)
      - Universities Teaching Chinese and Japanese (Box 11)
      - Department of State Questionnaire (Box 11)
      - Chinese Materials and Research Aids Service Center, Inc. (Box 11)
      - Irick project (Box 11)
      - Japanese Elites (Box 11)
      - North East Regional Council (Box 11)
      - Mekong Valley Project (Box 11)
      - Exchange-Visitor Program Number (Box 11)
      - Inter University Consortium on Political Research (Box 11)
      - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO (Box 11)
      - Southeast Asia Geographers Conference (Box 11)
      - Conference on Asian Affairs (Box 11)
      - Conference on Modern Japan, 4 folders (Box 11)
      - Midwest Conference on Asian Affairs (Box 11)
      - Conference on Untouchables in India (Box 11)
      - Books and Periodicals Exchange (Box 11)
      - International Education Act of, 1966 (Box 11)
      - Southeast Asia Institute (Box 11)
      - Institute of Pacific Relations, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Translation Lists (Box 11)
      - Social Science Periodicals for Europe (Box 11)
      - National Archives Project (Box 11)
      - Research-Liaison Office for Far East Project (Box 11)
      - Project Proposals (Box 11)
      - State Department Projects (Box 11)
      - Council on Economic and Cultural Affairs (Box 12)
      - China Policy Statement, 1966 (Box 12)
      - Far East Association National Questionnaire (Box 12)
      - The Role of Area Oriented Professional Organizations (Box 12)
      - The Sharma Case (Box 12)
      - Asian Studies on the Pacific Coast (Box 12)
      - Secretary of State-Language Reform (Box 12)
      - India and Pakistan Question (Box 12)
      - Conference on Taisho Japan (Box 12)
      - China-Inner Asia Regional Council (Box 12)
      - Asia Society correspondence (Box 12)
      - Human Resources Area File, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - National Defense Education Act (Box 13)
      - Computerized Bibliography (Box 13)
    - Language and Area Studies Review
      - Organizations
        - Area Associations-General (Box 13)
        - African Studies Association-Correspondence (Box 13)
        - African Studies Association-History (Box 13)
        - American Association for the Advancement of (Box 13)
        - Slavic Studies-Correspondence (Box 13)
        - American Association for the Advancement of (Box 13)
        - Slavic Studies-History (Box 13)
        - American Oriental Society-Correspondence (Box 13)
        - American Oriental Society-History (Box 13)
        - Association of Asian Studies-Correspondence (Box 13)
        - Association of Asian Studies-History (Box 13)
        - Latin American Studies Association-Correspondence (Box 13)
        - Latin American Studies Association-History (Box 13)
        - Middle East Studies Association Correspondence (Box 13)
        - Middle East Studies Association History (Box 13)
      - Project files
        - Area Studies Review Contract (Box 13)
        - Survey Project Proposal and Report (Box 13)
        - Language and Area Studies Review (Box 13)
        - Interface Inc. (Box 13)
        - National Computer Systems, Inc. (Box 13)
        - Ehrman, Edith-Correspondence (Box 13)
        - Office of Education (Box 13)
        - Progress Reports (Box 13)
        - Publicity (Box 13)
        - Lambert, Richard-Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Inter-Office and Memos (Box 13)
        - Council of Executive Secretary of Area Associations (Box 13)
        - Automated Information Systems-Conference (Box 13)
        - Econometric Society (Box 13)
        - Equipment Information (Box 13)
        - Administrative Meetings-Association Historians, 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Personnel File (Box 13)
        - Tilman Survey (Box 13)
        - Related Surveys (Box 14)
        - Questionnaire-Student (Box 14)
        - Questionnaire-Contents (Box 14)
        - Questionnaire Hand Tailoring (Box 14)
        - Questionnaire Protest (Box 14)
        - Questionnaire Processing (Box 14)
        - Inventory of Individual Area Competences Questionnaire (Box 14)
        - Related Correspondence (Box 14)
        - International Studies Association Returns (Box 14)
        - Area Faculty Questionnaire (Box 14)
        - Directory Information (Box 14)
        - Design and Format (Box 14)
        - Questionnaire Returns (Box 14)
    - Far Eastern Association Meeting File
      - 1949-1957, 17 folders (Box 14)
      - 1958-1968, 9 folders (Box 15)
    - Regional Meeting and Conferences File:
      - South Asia Regional Council (Box 15)
      - Southeast Asia Regional Council (Box 15)
      - Midwest Conference on Asian Affairs (Box 15)
      - Metropolitan New York Meeting (Box 15)
      - Upstate New York Regional Meeting (Box 15)
      - Northeast Asia Regional Council (Box 15)
      - Western Conference (Box 15)
      - Institutes and Regional Meetings (Box 15)
      - Regional meetings, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Biggerstaff, Knight-Correspondence (Box 15)
      - New England Regional Meeting (Box 15)
      - Asian Studies on the Pacific Coast (Box 15)
      - Southeastern Regional Meeting (Box 15)
    - International Congress of Orientalists (I.C.O.) File:
      - International Congress of Orientalists Lists (Box 16)
      - Argentines (Box 16)
      - Fifield, Russell, Secretary General (Box 16)
      - Harper Orientalists Congress (Box 16)
      - International Congress of Orientalist, Leningrad, 1960; 1963 (Box 16)
      - 26th International Congress of Orientalist, 1963 (Box 16)
      - White House Correspondence (Box 16)
      - Uralic and Actaic Studies (Box 16)
      - Von Grunebaum, G.E.' (Box 16)
      - International Union of Orientalists (Box 16)
      - Committee of Three (Box 16)
      - Library Panel (Box 16)
      - Hall, John W.-Japan (Box 16)
      - U.N. Secretary General U Thant (Box 16)
      - American Council of Learned Societies (Box 16)
      - Organizing Committee Minutes (Box 16)
      - Orientalists Congress Book Exhibit (Box 16)
      - Organizing Committee Memos (Box 16)
      - Organizing Committee-Correspondence (Box 16)
      - Asia Foundation (Box 16)
      - Natural Science Foundation Grant (Box 16)
      - National Endowment for the Humanities (Box 16)
      - State Department Correspondence (Box 16)
      - Institutional Invitations (Box 16)
      - Secretary General (Box 16)
      - Disbursements (Box 16)
      - Brown, W. Norman (Box 16)
      - Institutional Invitations-Acceptance (Box 16)
      - I.C.O. Attendance List (Box 16)
      - Orientalist Congress Bid, 1967 (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Lecture Files:
      - Grant Applications-International Congress (Box 17)
      - Nirmal Kumar Rose (Box 17)
      - Ruben Santos Coyugan (Box 17)
      - Wang Gungwu (Box 17)
      - Senarat Paranavitana (Box 17)
      - Daw Mya Sein (Box 17)
      - U Thittila (Box 17)
      - E. Maung (Box 17)
      - Asia Foundation Lectureship (new Series) (Box 17)
      - Asia Foundation Lectureship U Nu (Box 17)
      - Miscellaneous material (Box 17)
  - 1949-1985, 1970-1979
    - Administrative Officer Correspondence (Carol Johnson Chronological File)
      - January 1971-December 1975, 20 folders (Box 18)
      - January 1976-December 1980, 13 folders (Box 19)
    - American Council of Learned Societies, 1970-1974 (Box 19)
    - American Institute of Indian Studies
      - 1972 (Box 19)
      - 1972-1975 (Box 20)
    - Annual Meeting of AAS
      - 1949-1963, 15 folders (Box 20)
      - 1964-1971, 8 folders (Box 21)
      - 1972-1974, 4 folders (Box 22)